"Food Poisoning:
Causes and Prevention"
Remember that 24-hour flu
you had last year?
Well, there is no such thing
as a 24- or 48-hour flu.
There is no such thing
as stomach flu.
What you had
is likely food poisoning.
When someone gets hepatitis
from eating a strawberry,
the hepatitis didn't come
from the strawberry;
berries don't have
little livers.
As Dr. McDougall liked to ask,
when is the last time
we heard of someone getting
Dutch elm disease
or a bad case of aphids?
Just as virtually
all known human pandemics
come from animals originally,
so does most food poisoning,
specifically animal feces,
and that manure runoff
can contaminate
sprout seeds, spinach,
and other healthy plant foods.
Still, that's better
than eating the manure directly.
Animal products,
particularly fish and poultry,
can be covered
in fecal bacteria.
It's so bad that while
the U.S. federal government
recommends that we wash
our fruits and vegetables,
we're not supposed
to rinse meat
for fear of the viral
and bacterial splatter.
It's even been put to the test,
and indeed,
washing chicken in the sink
under standard
kitchen faucet conditions
can spew droplets containing
culturable levels of pathogens
throughout the kitchen.
Meat is so covered
in fecal matter residue
that researchers found more
fecal matter in the kitchen--
on sponges, dish towels,
and sink drains--
than they found
swabbing the toilet.
Even after repeatedly cleaning
everything with bleach,
it may be safer to lick
the rim of the toilet seat
than the kitchen countertop,
because people aren't preparing
chickens in their toilets.
That chicken "juice"
in the cellophane
is more like fecal soup.
As described by the head
of the food inspectors' union:
"You take a chicken
that eats, sleeps, craps,
and everything else
in one space,
they enter the scald vat dirty,
and it takes only a few minutes
to become just
brown fecal soup."
And that's what leaks
out of the chicken later
in the meat case.
No wonder poultry accounts for
more food poisoning outbreaks
than any other food.
And, according to the U.S.
General Accounting Office,
contaminated poultry products
also cause the most deaths.
This is because two
of the most significant causes
of hospitalizations and death,
Campylobacter and Salmonella,
are found in poultry.
Campylobacter is a fecal poultry
pathogen that can trigger
something called
Guillain-Barré syndrome,
where you come down
with Campylobacter
food poisoning once,
and then you can end up
paralyzed on a ventilator.
You're not in a coma;
you're awake,
but you can be
so completely paralyzed
you can't even
breathe on your own,
like straight out
of a buried-alive horror movie.
According to the
U.S. Department of Agriculture,
nearly half of chicken quarters
or halves in the United States
are contaminated
with this pathogen.
But Campylobacter isn't
the leading cause
of food poisoning
hospitalizations.
That's Salmonella,
which is also the leading cause
of foodborne death.
An investigation
by Consumer Reports
found widespread
Salmonella contamination;
31 percent
of ground chicken samples
taken from grocery stores
across the U.S.
were found to be tainted
with Salmonella.
All the Salmonella they found
was resistant
to at least one antibiotic,
and 78 percent were resistant
to multiple drugs.
That's one of the reasons
Salmonella is the leading reason
people can die
from a single meal.
It's difficult to treat
human Salmonella infections
because they're
becoming resistant
to so many of our
miracle drug antibiotics.
After the Jack in the Box
E. coli outbreak
in the early nineties,
E. coli O157:H7 was officially
deemed an adulterant,
meaning contaminated beef
could not be legally sold
and has to be recalled.
But the USDA has not taken
similar action
to protect the public
from Salmonella,
which is widespread
in chicken,
thanks to the often crowded
and filthy conditions
in which they are raised.
More than a million Americans
get sick from Salmonella
every year;
that's about five times more
than E. coli sickens,
yet the USDA looks the other way
if less than one in six chicken
parts is contaminated,
and even when those levels
are exceeded,
the meat still ends up
in grocery stores.
So, when you actually test
retail chicken parts,
more than 40 percent can be
contaminated with Salmonella.
Why is it that European nations
can boast so much lower
Salmonella contamination?
Because in Europe,
they require that their meat
is Salmonella free.
They still find some
Salmonella-contaminated flocks,
but the difference is that
it is illegal to sell
Salmonella-positive
chicken there.
Banning contaminated poultry
is a "hard-handed" policy,
an Alabama poultry science
professor explains:
"The fact is
that it's just too expensive
not to sell
Salmonella-positive chicken."
Let that sink in for a moment.
That's like
a toy manufacturer saying,
"Sorry, we'd love to pull
the unsafe toys from the market,
but such a large percentage
of our toys are hazardous,
that would just be
too expensive."
In 2023, the USDA at least
proposed that we shouldn't allow
Salmonella in products like raw
frozen breaded poultry products
that consumers may undercook.
What did the National Chicken
Council have to say?
The poultry industry
was gravely concerned.
Not about all the graves
created by their products,
but the "200 million
servings of this product
[that] will be lost."
This is the poultry industry
admitting
that they are producing hundreds
of millions of servings
of Salmonella-contaminated
chicken every year.
In terms of fish hygiene,
researchers swabbed sushi
for fecal bacteria.
Nearly all samples violated
international
food safety standards.
They also tested cucumber
and avocado rolls
and found
no fecal contamination,
perhaps because, unlike salmon,
tuna, and shrimp,
fruits and vegetables
don't have rectums.
Though the E. coli
may not necessarily
come from fish butts,
as higher E. coli counts
were found
when sushi was prepared
with bare hands,
compared to gloved.
What percentage of other meat
may come prepackaged with poop?
Anywhere from
a quarter to two thirds.